Guide to Maurice Isserman Research Files for The Other American: The Life of Michael Harrington TAM.239
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
Maurice Isserman Research Files for The Other American: The Life of Michael Harrington
Bulk, 1970-1995
1940-1995
TAM.239
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
4.0 linear feet (5 boxes)
Maurice Isserman is an historian and author of The Other American: The Life of Michael Harrington (2000), and several other books relating to the history of the American left. The collection contains interview transcripts, topical files, newspaper clippings by and about Harrington, and FOIA files obtained by Isserman. Prominent interviewees include: William F. Buckley, Lewis Coser, Norman Dorsen, Hal Draper, Harry Fleischman, John K. Galbraith, Herbert Gans, Michael Harrington (there are also two interviews of Harrington conducted by others), his wife Stephanie Harrington, Irving Howe, Irving Kristol, David McReynolds, Jack Newfield, Victor Reuther, Eugene Rostow, Andre Schiffrin, Stanley Sheinbaum, and Diana Trilling.
Isserman, Maurice
Box 1-5
Historical/Biographical Note
Maurice Isserman is an historian and author of The Other American: The Life of Michael Harrington (2000), and of Which Side Are You On?: The American Communist Party during the Second World War, and If I Had a Hammer: The Death of the Old Left and the Birth of the New Left (1993). Isserman is also a professor of history at Hamilton College (New York).
Michael Harrington (1928-1989), is best known as the author of The Other America: Poverty in the United States (1962), and as the founder and leader of the Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee, which later became the Democratic Socialists of America (U.S. affiliate of the Socialist International). He also taught political science at Queens College, part of the City University of New York, and continued to write, lecture and travel widely until his death from cancer in 1989. Among his many books were two autobiographical works, Taking Sides: The Education of a Militant Mind(1985) and The Long-Distance Runner: An Autobiography(1987), The New American Poverty(1984), The Politics at God's Funeral: The Spiritual Crisis of Western Civilization(1985), and Socialism: Past and Future(1989).
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Separated Materials
Separated from the collection were: (a) 14 videocassettes of public programs featuring or about Michael Harrington, which were transferred to the Library’s NonPrint collection, and: (b) 116 audiocassettes, apparently the oral history interviews whose transcripts comprise series I, which were transferred to the Library’s Sound collection.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Maurice Isserman Oral History Interviews
Arrangement
The collection is organized into four series: I, Interview transcripts (arranged alphabetically); II, Topical files (arranged alphabetically); III, Newspaper clippings (arranged chronologically); IV, FOIA files (arranged by file number).
Scope and Contents note
The collection is organized into four series: I, Interview transcripts; II, Topical files; III, Newspaper clippings; IV, FOIA files. Prominent interviewees include: William F. Buckley, Lewis Coser, Norman Dorsen, Hal Draper, Harry Fleischman, John K. Galbraith, Herbert Gans, Michael Harrington (there are also two interviews of Harrington conducted by others), his wife Stephanie Harrington, Irving Howe, Irving Kristol, David McReynolds, Jack Newfield, Victor Reuther, Eugene Rostow, Andre Schiffrin, Stanley Sheinbaum, and Diana Trilling. The topical files contain background material on people, organizations and issues. The newspaper clippings consist of articles by and about Michael Harrington. The four FOIA files were obtained by Isserman.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Maurice Isserman sent a gift of research files, videocassettes, and audiocassettes related to Michael Harrington in December 2000. The accession number associated with this gift is 2000.024.
Buckley, William F. (William Frank), 1925-2008; Democratic Socialists of America.; Denitch, Bogdan Denis; Dorsen, Norman; Draper, Hal; Fleischman, Harry.; Fund for the Republic.; Glotzer, Albert, 1908-1999.; Harrington, Michael, 1928-1989; Haskell, Gordon.; Howe, Irving.; Isserman, Maurice; Jacobson, Julius; Kristol, Irving.; League for Industrial Democracy.; McReynolds, David.; Meyerson, Harold .; Noṿiḳ, P., 1891-; Rawick, George P., 1929-; Rosenberg, Bernard, 1923-1996; Schiffrin, Andre; Schwartz, Joseph.; Social Democrats, USA.; Trilling, Diana; Clippings (information artifacts); Government records.; Interviews.; Political scientists |z United States |v Biography.; Research (document genres).; Socialism |z United States |x History.; Socialists |z United States |v Biography.
- Series I: Interview Transcripts
  - Berthelme, Elizabeth, March 17, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bernstein, Jules, March 9, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Booth, Heather, March 11, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Brungard, Ed, December 14, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Buckley, William F., January 6, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chapin, Jim, April/December 1991 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Clark, Ed, March 23, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Clark, Jack, January/March 1991 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Clingon, Eldon, May 19, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Corbin, Marty & Ed Egan, October 30, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Coser, Lewis, May 3, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Dempsey, Richard, May 16, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Denitch, Betty, August 6, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Denitch, Bogdan, 1984-1991 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Diaz, Eileen Fautino, March 16, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Dorsen, Norman, May 24, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Draper, Hal, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Dreier, Peter, November 5, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Faherty, William Father, May 13, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Faucher, Ed, January 6, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Finn, Jim and Molly, September 27, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - FitzGibbon, Peggy, November 3, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Fitzsimmons, Richard, February 7, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Fleischman, Harry, April 6, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Franklin, Joan S., March 19, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Galbraith, John K., May 19, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Gallin, Liz, January 6, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Gans, Herb, March 16, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Geltman, Manny, March 19, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Gittin, Todd, June 16, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Glotzer, Al, October 10, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Hacker, David, August 19, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Harrington, Alec, September 27, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Harrington, Michael -- interviewed by John Cogley, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Harrington, Michael, November 19, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Harrington, Michael – interviewed by Kirkpatrick Sale, October 6, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Harrington, Michael and Dave, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Harrington, Stephanie, September 27, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Harrington, Ted, February 15, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Haskell, Gordon, July 15, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Healey, Richard, March 11, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Henle, Father, December 13, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Howe, Irving, undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Jacobson, Julius and Phyllis, undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Jordan, Ruth, March 10, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Kelman, Steve, November 24, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Kristol, Irving, August 8, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Kusnet, Dave, March 11, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Kuttner, Bob, April 26, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Lacefield, Patrick and Dinah Lewenthal, August 5, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Levinson, Mark, July 24, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Lipon, Arthur, November 9, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Llewelyn, Frank, October 14, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Loftus, Bill, September 27, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Max, Steve, May 14, 1986; October 16, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - McGovern, Hamilton, April 14, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - McReynolds, Dave, July 9, 1984; September 16, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Meier, Debbie, April 19, 1986; January 6, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Meyerson, Harold, July 27, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Mitchell, Peggy Brennan, October 22, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Moore, Arthur J., September 28, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Mort, Jo-Ann, September 26, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Murphy, Joe, October 16, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Newfield, Jack, January 6, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Nichols, Marcy Perot, March 16, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Novick, Peter, December 28, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - O’Brien, Dave, September 13, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - O’Gorman, Ned, May 23, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - O’Neill, Roger, April 6, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Padburg, John S.J., February 13, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Rawick, George, August 17, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Reinert, Paul C. S.J., December 13, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Reuther, Victor, August 6, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Roberts, Skip, August 6, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Rosenberg, Bernie, October 6, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Rostow, Eugene, August 6, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Schori, Pierre, June 11, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Schiffrin, Andre, June 19, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Schwartz, Joe, February 8, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Shier, Carl, November 4, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Shier, Nancy and Roberta Lynch, April 3, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Sheinbaum, Stanley K., July 29, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Schoch, Jim, October 23, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Silbiger, Steve, March 10, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Stanley, John, July 25, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Steinfels, Peter, October 14, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Stillman, Dan, undated (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - Stuart, Jack, January 7, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - Thomas, Bill -- notes on interview with, January 10, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Thyessen, Freijof, December 8, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - Towey, Martin, May 14, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - Trilling, Diana, July 25, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - Tristman, Dorothy and Larry Wittner, July 4, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 93)
  - Wakefield, Dan, February 7, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 94)
  - Walzer, Michael, March 20, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 95)
  - Warwick, Jane, January 6, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 96)
  - Wilkerson, Jerome Msgr, May 13, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 97)
  - Zimmerman, Fred Father, December 13, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 98)
- Series II: Topical Files
  - Chicago, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Civil Rights, 1959-1992 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Conservatives, 1980s (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Democratic Agenda, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Democratic Socialists of America, 1983-1989 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - DSOC, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Fund for the Republic, circa 1956 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Harrington, Michael - family, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Harrington, Michael - family, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Harrington, Michael - illness, 1985-1989 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Holy Cross, 1945-1991 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Howe, Irving, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Ireland, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Jews & Israel, 1970-1992 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Labor Movement, 1965-1994 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - League for Industrial Democracy, 1964-1995 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - McReynolds, Dave, 1950s (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - New Left, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Queens College, 1975-1989 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Releases, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Reviews of Michael Harrington, 1965-1987 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Rustin, Baynard, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - St. Louis University High School, 1940-1944 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - SDUSA (Social Democrats, USA), 1986 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Shachtman / ISL, 1984-1996 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Socialism, history & future, 1970s (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Socialist International, 1977-1996 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Socialist Party, 1960s (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Socialist Party, 1960s (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Vietnam War, 1971-1993 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Village Voice, 1950s-1991 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Workers Defense League, 1984-1991 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Yale Law School, 1984-1992 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - YPSL (Young Peoples Socialist League), 1971-1991 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Series III: Newspaper Clippings by and about Michael Harrington
  - Harrington clippings, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Harrington clippings, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Harrington clippings, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Harrington clippings, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Harrington clippings, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Harrington clippings, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Harrington clippings, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Harrington clippings, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Harrington clippings, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Harrington clippings, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Harrington clippings, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Harrington clippings, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Harrington clippings, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Harrington clippings, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Harrington clippings, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Harrington clippings, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Harrington clippings, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Harrington clippings, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Harrington clippings, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Harrington clippings, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Harrington clippings, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Harrington clippings, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Harrington clippings, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Harrington clippings, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Harrington clippings, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Harrington clippings, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Harrington clippings, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Harrington clippings, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Harrington clippings, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Harrington clippings, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Harrington clippings, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Harrington clippings, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Harrington clippings, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Harrington clippings, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Harrington clippings, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Harrington clippings, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Harrington clippings, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Harrington clippings, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Harrington clippings, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Series IV: FOIA FIles (by file number)
  - FOIPA HQ 100-411915 Vol. 1 - 1 out of 2 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - FOIPA HQ 100-411915 Vol. 1 - 2 out of 2 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - FOIPA HQ 100-411915 Vol. 2 - 1 out of 2 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - FOIPA HQ 100-411915 Vol. 2 - 2 out of 2 (Box 4, Folder 10)